Let's pray.
Good morning.
I wish there was, like, epic music that played whenever I entered a room. You know what I mean? You feeling that? Yeah. You know? Like, before I clock in to work, you know? Like, everyone's in the office, and all of a sudden, like, even just that would work. That backing track would work. You know? Like, what's happening? It's like, Sam must be arriving. You know what I mean?
Walk-up music. You know the movie? Yeah, walk-up music. You know, like, the movie The Emperor's New Groove? You guys seen that movie? It's one of the most underrated Disney films. And he, like, hums his own, like, theme music everywhere he goes. You know what I'm talking about? Yeah. It's like that. All right. Great. There's water here. All right. Well, I believe, if I'm not mistaken, Kent, this is the second to last sermon right in the series, and Kent's going to be finishing up next week. Is that right? Yeah.
Yeah. So there's a lot, as I'm sure we all know, to unpack in the Book of Revelation. And today, should I just keep powering through? Good? Okay. With the microphone? All right. There's a lot to go through in the Book of Revelation, of course, as you guys know. And so I would hope that as you continue your walk, that this be a book that you revisit, now that we've given you some tools to kind of demystify the book.
Right? And actually see how it applies in your daily life, because it does. Honestly, for, you know, I've been saved since I was a kid, and I've been in ministry for over 20 years. And it wasn't until like three years ago that I actually saw the Book of Revelation as a book that would actually have application in my daily life. So a lot of people are missing out on that opportunity. Just now that we've gone through this, I hope that you'll continue to revisit this book as we go. As we get started today,
I want you guys to think about something. Has anyone in this room, you don't have to show our hands or anything, but this is more for your own time of reflection. Anyone here, have you ever been involved in something? Maybe like a company, an organization, maybe a relationship, or just a group of relationships, a community, where you later found out that there were some really terrible things going on?
And you were somehow a part of it, and even unknowingly contributed to it. Anyone ever have to happen? Where like, "Wow, my hands are dirty," was something that I didn't even realize was happening.
I can think of a few in my own life. Some of the most painful ones have been when I've been close to somebody,
and welcomed someone into my life as a good friend, and only to find out that they were doing a lot of harm to other people that I cared about.
And telling those people that I was in agreement with the harm they were doing, unbeknownst to me, only to find out later that that was going on.
Right? Anyone ever have anything like that? Maybe a workplace? Maybe friendships? More than one thing. How did that make you feel?
To find out that you were complicit in evil and dark things that you would have never agreed to, or even really opened your eyes to seeing what was happening.
How did you, how did it make you rethink maybe your time, your words, or your actions?
I can think of that one particular situation where I thought back to some things that I said, and I was like, oh my gosh, I was playing into lies being told, and I didn't even know it.
Right, so now I'm rethinking my words, and my choices, and all these kinds of things. Am I doing something wrong with the mic, or is that, just keep going?
All right, I don't want to blow everybody's ears.
So it's a terrible feeling if you've been through it, right? It's a terrible feeling to know that you were complicit in things like that.
And today, I want us to imagine that feeling at a much grander and more eternal scale.
At the end of all things, when our lives are evaluated, I want us to think about that.
That's going to be the goal of today's lesson as we're reading through. We're going to be in Revelation chapter 17 and 18.
So again, we're nearly through this series, so you guys have heard this a lot, but for anyone who's new, I just want us to understand our goal in the book of Revelation.
We are studying Revelation not to decode the future, but to understand what is truly going on behind the scenes in the world, and how we can live wisely in light of what's going on behind the scenes.
Revelation was written to persecuting or struggling and some complacent Christians, and it was written to call them to true devotion to Christ.
By constantly focusing on the victory of Christ, as we see constantly through the book of Revelation, the victory of Christ over the systems of the world,
Revelation calls us to endure through hardship, with faithfulness, to worship God with our whole self, and to place God's priorities at the top of ours, even if it costs us our lives.
So, you know, just a bit of light reading today. It's going to be a really easy topic.
No worries. All right? Revelation 17 to 18, the chapters we're going to be in today, the chapters we'll be looking at are expanding, actually, on the judgments on Babylon that we saw at the very end of chapter 16 last week.
Ryan spoke with you guys at chapter 16, the seven bowls of that judgment. And so, you can really think of Revelation 17 to 18 as taking the seventh bowl and just kind of stretching it out and thinking about it through different
dynamics and analogies. Does that make sense? It's going to expound on it. Both of these chapters really are expounding on the seventh bowl from the last chapter.
And they're doing so from really two different angles, capturing multiple dimensions of a complex and the corrupt systems of the world.
Okay? That's what we're going to see. By considering the direct references to the Roman Empire, which we'll see in these passages, there's direct references to the Roman Empire in John's day.
What we're going to be forced to consider, buckle up, okay? Because we're not just talking about Rome. Nobody here lives in Rome anymore, right? At least not that Roman Empire.
As we consider the correlations to the Roman Empire of John's day, we're going to have to consider the correlations to the governments and the nation and the systems in which we live today, right?
Revelation wasn't just about the Roman Empire, and now that they're gone, everything's a bowl of cherries.
Okay? There's a pattern to the way that human systems always tend to operate and gravitate towards, right? And so we're going to be forced to consider how Babylon manifests in our modern day, our modern day systems, our modern day economics, and our modern day politics, okay?
Also, we're in the book of Revelation. Get ready, once again, for some graphic descriptions. All the kids are out, okay? Don't worry. Hopefully, no small children will be learning the word "prostitute" this morning.
But if they're in this room, this is your parental guidance warning. That word is in this chapter a lot. So we're going to see some realities here.
And the reason it's so graphic and the reason it's so descriptive, but I want us to understand, it's not just being, like, flippant with the nature of these things.
The reason it's so graphic and descriptive is because the realities that are being alluded to are deeply evil and seductive and destructive.
And so these images help us wrestle with just how bad and seductive and corrupting these things are. Make sense?
All right, so we're going to open up. We're going to read just the first six verses of Revelation.
If you've got your Bibles with you, let's go ahead and turn there if you haven't already.
We're going to be in Revelation 17:1, okay?
And so we're going to see here John's vision from, really specifically, Revelation 16:19 is going to be expanding on in this chapter.
So verse 1, it says, "One of the seven angels who had poured out the seven bowls came over and spoke to me.
Come with me," he said, "and I will show you the judgment that is going to come on the great prostitute who rules over many waters.
The kings of the world have committed adultery with her, and the people who belong to this world have been
made drunk by the wine of her immorality. So the angel took me in the spirit into the wilderness, and there I saw a woman
sitting on a scarlet beast that had seven heads and ten horns, and blasphemies against God were written all over it.
The woman wore purple and scarlet clothing and beautiful jewelry made of gold and precious gems and pearls.
In her hand, she held a gold goblet full of obscenities and the impurities of her immorality. A mysterious name was written
on her forehead, Babylon the Great, mother of all prostitutes and obscenities in the world. And I could see that she was
drunk, drunk with the blood of God's holy people who were witnesses for Jesus. And I stared at her in complete
amazement. As you read on through chapter 17, you're going to see the angel explains that the scarlet beast
that she's writing is the same one from Revelation 13, if you guys recall back to that message. And further
explains some of the symbology that John is seeing, which we'll get to in a minute. And then this weird thing, the
chapter actually ends with the beast that she's writing, turning on her and devouring her and
destroying her. Okay. So some weird images. All right. So we're going to unpack some of this a little bit
today. What are we seeing here in this first chapter, in chapter 17? We're seeing, first of all, the
prostitute, which is identified as Babylon, right? And this is an image we've already seen come up through
Revelation multiple times and continues here. Right? This prostitute is a picture of the seductive,
idolatrous culture and spirituality of the world. And this idolatrous, spiritual culture is materialistic
and pleasure-focused to the degree of exploiting, corrupting, and destroying people.
And throughout biblical prophecy, idolatry, you might be wondering, okay, why a prostitute? Like I get the
seductive, you know, the corruptive, all these kinds of things. Why prostitute? Throughout biblical
prophecy, idolatry is pictured consistently as prostitution and adultery because it captures the
essence of what is happening when people turn from God to worship other things. Right?
The right standing of humanity and all human systems is to be married to God, right? You
guys understand that? And so every other thing, there's not a middle ground, right? We like
to say, "Oh, well, I'm worshiping God. I'm worshiping the devil." Or, you know, I'm just
kind of in the middle, just kind of doing nothing. This is not true. If you think you're in the
middle doing nothing, you're sleeping with the prostitute. This is what the image is trying
to get you to see, right? There's God and there's Babylon, right? And so there's this seductive, crafty
nature. You notice how the people are drunk? Notice how she is drunk, right? These images
are conveying this idea, right, of trickery and delusion and intoxication with the things
of the world. Like if we were to step back and look at them, like John, right? John has been living
in the Croesus. He's living in the Roman Empire, right? And John is getting a look at the Roman
Empire from different lengths. And he's like, "You know, Roma, like the lady on the coins and like the
seven hills of Rome, blah, blah, blah." He's like, "Back up. It's a prostitute on a seven-headed beast
drunk with the blood of the Christians." And John's like, "Oh, I've never really quite looked
at it like this before." Right? See, that's the vision. And so John's vision also captures how
widespread and comprehensive this Babylon's influence and control really is. Think about
it. It's holding both kings to the very top of human society and the rulers of the
governments. Both kings are blending with this, right? They've been committing adultery because,
again, they should have been married to God and his kingdom and ruling with justice over the nations
that they serve. But instead, they're committing adultery with the prostitute. And even the common
people are drunk on the wine that she's giving them. You see that, right? Just heavy
imagery here, right? We've got to let it soak for a minute because it's holding both kings
and common people under its sway. Then the beast we see in this chapter is, let's put it this way,
whereas the prostitute, right, Babylon is representing cultures, religions, economic
systems, the beast represents military and political power. So you see the picture
here of how those all go together, right? Who's writing who in the image, right? The
military and the political power is being ridden by a more seductive and
corruptive culture, false religion, idolatry against God, right? Exploitation
of human lives. And so the angel explains that the beast's heads and
horns are like this complex symbol of political power and military
might, representing specific kings in history and empires as actually
reference points for repeating patterns that go on throughout time.
And so when you look at the images and you're like, you know, there's five kings
have already come, and there's seven, there's two that aren't coming yet, and
there's one who's really the eighth, but he's part of the seven, and you're like,
whoa, if you read into it, it's like, what are you talking about? It's a complex
symbol. It's like, well, are you talking about the Roman empires? It's like, yes.
Are you talking about just empires in general? Also, yes, right? So it's a complex
symbol. But the beast is symbolizing this military and political power, which by
the way is also often worshiped. Isn't it? Isn't military and
political power also worshiped as much as pleasure and money? Yeah. Yeah.
It's like all over. It's like you look at things happening today, and then you
rewind the clock like 2,000 years, and you're like, oh, yeah, yeah. It's a
Monday. You know, it's the same stuff every day, right? This is the way that these
systems work. And so then verse 18, though, loops back to
show the prostitute rules over the components that make up the beast. Isn't
that interesting? Right? The chapter ends with the beast, the
military and political power, turning and devouring, hating the prostitute, right?
Hating Babylon and devouring it. And then it ends and it goes, but she rules
over all the components that make up the beast. That's the last verse of that
chapter, right? And when the beast devours and destroys the prostitute,
it's a picture of how God judges these corrupt systems by letting them destroy
themselves, which by the way, they ultimately do. Right?
If you study history at all, you will see this progression
where nations and governments and hegemonies
and whatever you want to call them, right? They go up like this. They get corrupt.
They corrupt. They exploit more and more and more people.
They do more and more and more damage and bloodshed.
And then they completely collapse. Right?
That's what happened in the Roman Empire. Right?
That's what happened in multiple empires things.
That's what's happening, let's be honest, to empires as we speak.
And so what we see there in the chapter is it's like God put this idea
in the beast's head to turn and devour the prostitute, right?
So even when we see these systems destroy themselves from within,
even then the angel is going, "That's God's judgment on them."
And you're going to see the cycle repeat.
Okay? So those are the images we're seeing there.
All right. So how is this happening now?
These images reveal the true nature, again, of all human systems, philosophies,
religions, cultures, and governments that do not submit to God.
Again, there are no neutral ones.
The lie of being neutral, of being, well, there's great following God, and there's obviously evil.
And then there's like these guys in the middle who are just kind of like, you know, minding their own business.
And it's not the best. You know, I know it's not the best. Right?
But it's like, oh, you're just, we're just being duped.
That's the prostitute, man. You're being seduced into engaging in these same things.
These images reveal the true nature of corrupt world systems that do not submit to God.
They are characterized by their self-glorification, by their hedonism.
That's just the pursuit of pleasure, right? Personal pleasure.
They're characterized by the exploitation of people, which often goes hand in hand with hedonism, by the way, right?
Think about how many pleasures people in our culture enjoy at the expense of others.
And the idolization of states' power.
So we must take special note of how seductive and enticing they can be. If you're thinking about the images in this chapter, right,
and the whining and the adultery and the prostitution and the sex and all these kinds of things, it's like, what's all this talking about?
You really have to open your eyes to how quickly and easily you can be pulled in.
This is what the image is trying to help us understand. Because we, can I just say it, like, look, we get duped a lot.
You guys understand that? We get duped a lot. Oh, it's not that bad.
It's not that bad. If you're saying it's not that bad, it's bad.
You know, like, no one ever says it's not that bad when they're talking about obviously great things.
You know what I mean? Okay.
All human systems and cultures that don't submit to God eventually implode and self-destruct.
And we see this over and over again throughout history.
All right, now we're going to go to Revelation 18, next chapter. I'm going to read just the first eight verses here.
Because we're going to see the same thing, destruction of Babylon, and now we're going to go from a different angle on it.
The last one was like this vision, this apocalyptic vision and images that John is seeing.
And now this next part becomes very auditory. It's very poetic. There's songs.
The whole chapter is basically poems and songs. The middle of the chapter are like dirges,
which is a fancy old word for like a funeral song, like a song of grief and mourning, right?
And so the second chapter almost becomes a totally different literary genre, right?
Because now we're going to look at a different angle of it.
And we're going to see the shifting from the apocalyptic visions of Revelation 17 to, again, like these poetic laments and these prophetic oracles.
And then we're going to unpack this, okay? Because there's a point to this in our lives that I really want to spend our time on this morning.
So Revelation 18:1-8 says, "After all this, I saw another angel come down from heaven with great authority, and the earth grew bright with his splendor."
And he gave a mighty shout, "Babylon is fallen. The great city is fallen. She has become a home for demons."
She is a hideout for every foul spirit, a hideout for every foul vulture and every foul and dreadful animal.
For all the nations have fallen because of the whine of her passionate immorality.
The kings of the world have committed adultery with her. Because of her desires for extravagant luxury, the merchants of the world have grown rich.
Then I heard another voice calling from heaven, "Come away from her, my people.
Do not take part in her sins, or you will be punished with her.
For her sins are piled as high as the heaven, and God remembers her evil deeds.
Do to her as she has done to others. Double her penalty for all of her evil deeds.
She brewed a cup of terror for others. So brew twice as much for her.
She glorified herself and lived in luxury. So match it now with torment and sorrow.
She boasted in her heart, "I am queen on my throne. I'm no helpless widow. I have no reason to mourn.
Therefore, these plagues will overtake her in a single day. Death and mourning and famine, and she will be completely consumed by fire.
The Lord God who judges her is mighty." Now, as we then read on through chapter 18, we're going to see two different responses.
And this is what I want us to really wrestle with today. There's two different responses to the destruction of Babylon that we're going to see.
While Revelation 17 established the identity of Babylon, you know, the state cultural anti-God system,
Revelation 18 focuses on Babylon's economic seduction, her systemic exploitation, and her absolute destruction.
The chapter goes on as those who indulged in and benefited from Babylon's systems all mourn over her destruction and their loss.
If you go on, it's just like, and then the kings, they begin to mourn, and they have this poem. And then the merchants, they begin to mourn.
And all of them are basically like, "Oh no. Everything we've enjoyed, all of our livelihood is gone," which is the point of God's judgment, right?
It concludes with a powerful picture, the millstone thrown into the sea.
You guys know where the Roman Empire sits? It's not a trick question.
It's not in the Mediterranean Sea. Grab a globe, okay? It's right there. It's kind of a big deal.
A lot of world history has happened in the Mediterranean Sea. I'm joking. Just trying to cut that tension, okay?
Yeah, so think about the imagery, right? John's day, he knows what we're talking about, the Roman Empire.
By the way, it's one in a series of empires, okay? And the chapter ends with his angel coming and going, "I would like to give you an object lesson."
He grabs a millstone, throws it into the Mediterranean Sea, and goes, "That's what's going to happen."
And you can imagine the picture and the imagery. You throw a millstone into the Mediterranean Sea.
You're getting that thing back? That thing coming back out of there? Not in their day, right?
So that's how it concludes, because it's showing, listen, what God, this is what I want us to wake up to, okay?
What God is about to do to Babylon is not going to be reversed. Babylon's not going to have a comeback.
Babylon's not going to have a renewal. Babylon, after centuries and millennia of cycling, Babylon is going to be judged.
And it's going to the bottom of the sea. So you need to come out. You need to come out.
From Babylon. Don't go down with it. You understand? So this is a powerful thing we see right in the chapter.
All right. So the imagery, right? The response of the kings. Because I said we see two responses.
The responses of the kings and the merchants and mariners, as you read through the rest of 18,
their response to Babylon's destruction all highlight how deeply embedded and even dependent people
can become, guys. All right. Listen, I'm not trying to be super political here because that's like,
I don't even like either one of our political parties. So like, if you're in the neutral camp,
come, we'll get coffee afterwards. Okay? I'm not trying to be specific, but guys, let's just be objective
about where we live. We live in the most powerful, wealthy nation, not only that exists today, and by the way,
it's a wide margin. It is. You wouldn't know from watching the news. It's a wide margin.
Not only do we live in the most powerful and wealthy and extravagant nation in the world today,
we live in the most powerful, wealthy, and extravagant nation that has ever existed on the planet
since the beginning of human history. Have you guys noticed that when we want countries to stop existing,
we just kind of like can make it happen? Okay? That should wake us up to the kind of nation that we live in.
Okay? So as we're thinking about John, we might go, "Not America!" Listen, I love America, guys. I'm down, right?
Red, white, and blue. Someone's like, "Are you free this weekend?" I'm like, "Bro, I'm free every weekend."
You know, like the eagle cries in the background. You guys know that joke? You know? I'm free every weekend.
Look at the sky, eagle. You know? You smell hot dogs and apple pie. You know what I'm saying?
I'm not like anti-America, guys, but I'm saying, like, listen, we do need to be thoughtful of what John is seeing,
given the country in which we live. Okay. That being said, I'm going to say this again.
The responses of the kings, merchants, and mariners to Babylon's destruction highlight how deeply embedded
and even dependent people can become with exploitative, self-indulgent, and deeply evil systems.
Okay? That's the picture of drunk with her wine. You just know how many times that phrase pops back up?
They're drunk with their wine. And the whole middle of the chapter is all the, like, first of all, we should be happy about Babylon's destruction,
and yet all the kings, everyone in Begid, everyone profiting from the system, they're all like, "Oh no, this is the worst day ever.
All of our money is gone. All of our pleasures are gone. All of our joys are gone." And God's like, "Yeah."
Okay? The true reality of Babylon's evil and corruption is not just pictured, and I want this to sink in, right?
You guys understand, God is concerned with so much deeper things than just, like, you breaking his moral rules.
Real quick, there are moral rules, okay? Sometimes people say that, and they mean it as a way of getting around those.
There are, for sure, moral rules, and it's not even ambiguous what they are. We can talk about that more later.
But if you think that's, like, the main thing, look at where every single one of these indictments conclude.
The destruction of human lives. Of greatest value to God, because of his own choice, because of his own nature and his own love.
Of greatest value to God are the lives of human beings.
And so it's not just pictured in the economics and the politics.
It's pictured in the exploitation and the destruction of human lives, which is of great concern to God,
and is actually clearly his motivating force in the way that he judges Babylon, right?
He says, "Hey, everything she did to people, we're going to do it twice over.
She brewed this cup, we're going to brew the same cup twice as strong and make her chug it."
Like, very graphic, right? Because of what she did to systems? No, because of what she did to people.
This is clearly pictured in verse 12 and 13. Here's a little fun Bible nerd fact.
Verse 12 and 13, you go, there's like a whole like, I don't have it on the screen, there's a whole cargo list, right?
And it like goes through, you're like, "Wow, John is being hyper-specific with like, imports and exports here."
The reason is because it's the exact import list of Rome.
And you know what it concludes with?
It concludes with human lives as a commodity.
John's like, "Oh yeah, you know what I saw? The cargo list that matches Rome."
And it's gold, and it's silver, and it's wheat, and barley, blah, blah, blah, and all these things.
And human lives.
There it is. Thank you.
Human lives.
This is showing the true cost of the Roman economy to the original audience, right?
It's not just how, like, unfair, right, to use an American analogy, it's not just how unfair their tea taxes were, right?
Although, like, that's not cool.
It's deeper.
He's like, they're treating people like things that can be managed in the stock exchange.
So it's revealing that as well.
So how is this happening now?
Ooh, let's start on that.
If we are blind to the true nature and presence of Babylon in our culture and nation, we can find ourselves participating in and even benefiting from its corruption,
by idolatry and its exploitation of human lives.
And so again, there are two ways we can respond to Babylon and its destruction.
We can be so embedded, so entangled with it that we mourn and grieve and cry when we lose the things that we lose when God brings justice to it.
And by the way, then end up being destroyed alongside of it. So that's option one, okay?
As we see here in this chapter. Option one is, you can see a good thing like the destruction of a system like that as a terrible thing.
That's your first possible response, right?
Second response is the one that he directly commands us to have, which is, "Get out of there."
"Come out," he says, "from her, my people." "Come out, refuse to participate in it, and therefore share none of its guilt."
And are able to see God's justice on it as a good thing.
You guys notice the people group that's like, "Yes!" in the chapter, do you read on, are God's people.
They're like, "Finally, you have brought judgment on the thing that killed all of us and destroyed so many lives."
And so in our own day, here we're going to get to the application for us this morning, okay?
In our own day, we have to consider which one of those two responses we're going to have.
Okay? We've got to think about which one of those two people we're going to be.
We all know what the right one is, okay? So let's not do a Sunday school answer.
Like, "Oh, I'm option B. That's me."
I have $30,000 in credit card debt, but that's me. I'm on, you know, B, you know, right?
Sorry. I'm not trying to shame people with credit card debt. It's a real problem.
But what I'm saying is, we're indebted to things because we're embedded in things.
And we've been drunk on the wine, and we're enslaved. And we need to wake up, right?
And we need to wake up. In our modern, multifaceted, and highly interconnected world,
we can find ourselves becoming entangled with Babylon, seduced by its offerings, right?
Like, our culture doesn't show up and be like, "Hey, I would like to exploit and abuse people. Do you want to come?"
You'd be like, "No, I'm not a monster." But it's like, "Hey, would you like to look at porn tonight?"
Which is the same thing. It's like, "Oh, well, I feel great if I do that." So yes.
That's a very extreme, crass example. More common than we like to admit.
But there's so many other ways in which we do the same thing.
Gain delight, and enjoyment, and security, and safety at great expense.
Because we've been seduced by its offerings.
We're compromising with its methods. This is another way that we get trapped.
Right?
You guys know the phrase, "The ends justify the means."
Right? It's been around, unfortunately, for several centuries.
Renaissance guy thought it up. He was an idiot. He's completely wrong. It's not true.
I'm sure he was smart in some other ways.
I can't remember his name off the top of my head. Machiavelli, that guy.
Maybe he had some things that he figured out. I don't know.
That wasn't one of them.
The ends do not justify the means.
You can't live like that.
And the most important part about that statement is that God is in disagreement with that statement.
So you're going to have to work that out if you want to go that way of thinking.
But we can compromise with Babylon's methods.
Well, you know, I know this is bad, but we're going to do some good over here.
So, you know, sometimes you got like, let's do two evils.
Cool. Yeah, we're compromising with its methods.
And ultimately, back to my analogy way of being in the sermon, right?
You ever been in a situation where you found out that you were complicit in something you would have never wanted to be complicit in?
Before we know it, we look around and we go, "Oh, no."
I am participating in its sins, right?
This is why God says, again, "Come away from her, my people.
Do not take part in her sins, or you'll be punished along with her."
So, this requires a lot of wisdom, okay?
You guys understand, there's no way I could give a proper amount of analogies to help you pinpoint what these things are in your life.
I'm talking in generalities because it's complex, and for every one of us in this room, it's going to be probably some slightly different things.
There'll be a lot in common, but there's going to be a lot that are specific to us, right?
So, it's going to require, just like it says in the Scripture, this requires wisdom.
It requires some thoughtful evaluation to identify.
Don't be knee-jerk, by the way. Like, don't.
Anyone here, like, a knee-jerk person, where you hear a sermon, and you're like, "I'm going to go do it!"
And then, like, you know, like, you're selling your house, and, like, moving to, like, Boxwanaland or something, and, like, everyone's like, "Where did he go?"
He's like, "I don't know."
He's using, like, natural deodorants now, and, like, you know, like, believes that, like, honey is the cure for everything or something, you know?
Or, like, you know, you can get, like, essential oils. I don't know, right? It's one of those things.
So, don't be a knee-jerk Christian and be like, "Got it! I'm going to go live in a hut in the wild and pretend that I'm, like, a sovereign citizen."
That's not what we're saying, okay? Like, if you do that, we're all going to be like, "Hey."
Let's reel that back in for a minute here, buddy, right? Let's not go nuts.
But we are going to have to be thoughtful and wise, and the disentanglement process needs to be thoughtful and wise and gradual.
If you're married, it needs to be agreed upon, right? This is a collaborative effort between you and your spouse and your family, okay?
So, don't get nuts on me, okay? But we do want to get thoughtful and begin to evaluate these things and go,
okay, I'm going to need to begin to disentangle some things here in a wise manner,
because I realize I'm participating in things I don't want to participate in, right?
Okay. How do we avoid this entanglement? So you might go, well, how do I just avoid it altogether? Great.
Our allegiance, this is why I want, think about this. Our allegiance and participation is actually largely decided by where we place our hope.
This is how you get drawn into things that you honestly wouldn't have otherwise chosen.
The world's system will seduce us with things like financial security and wealth.
Listen, you should all be wise. The Bible talks about that, being wise with your finances.
I'm not saying be like foolish and flippant, but I will also say I've always felt like financial security is an oxymoron.
Right? Okay. Something goes south in the stock market and everything you've worked for your entire life is gone, guys.
Okay? It's not that secure. Sorry to bust your bubble. Okay.
But we seduce by things like financial security and wealth. Wealth is very seductive.
I know we like to like hate the rich, right? But like wealth is very seductive, guys.
You have a hard time paying your bills. You've been struggling. You go through emergencies. We've all been there, right?
You know, sometimes, by the way, my wife's here finally today.
I say finally because like we just worked out we could actually both come. There's Andrea.
See, look, she's really as pretty as I've told you all that she is.
Okay. That was all right.
That's for me to say. Okay. Anyway.
Right?
But like the two of us have joked about like, you know, like, could you just give me like $5 million? Like things would be great.
I won't even spend it all, you know? So wealth can be very seductive.
You know what else is seductive? Cultural acceptance.
We have a lot of things, right?
We might say we're confrontational and we don't have to, you know, we don't have to go with the flow and we can buck the norm.
Like, mm-hmm, yeah, okay. Maybe in some areas. But guys, cultural acceptance is a real temptation and seduction.
Right?
You ever see like a pastor like on national television asked about a really controversial thing?
And they like, I mean, you would think they're like a figure skater, the way they're like moving around the question.
And you watch the guy's sermons and you know like the dude is totally against that thing.
But like on Good Morning America, he's like, "Well, that's a complex question for you."
Why? It's because of cultural acceptance is a real, right?
I'm not trying to downplay, it's a real weight.
Being the one person in the room that nobody agrees with is very emotionally difficult.
And it's a very easy temptation for the enemy for Babylon to draw us in.
I keep on going on tangents and losing my spy here, right?
But financial security, wealth, cultural acceptance.
And here's one that I think might be actually the hardest one for us to get over, guys.
Happiness and pleasure in this life.
Listen, if you're not happy, that's really hard.
I've been there this week, right?
Again, I'm not trying to downplay it.
We have to really be honest by how good the prostitute is at getting us to commit adultery.
Right?
Happiness and pleasure is probably the most seductive thing that we have to wrestle with.
Because it's not fun to not be happy.
Everything hurts, you know? Like the line from Parks and Rec, "Everything hurts and I'm dying." Right?
And so happiness, man, if I could just be happy.
You know, people are like, "I wish I could just be on vacation all the time."
I mean, that sounds nice.
You know, just for the record, if you actually spent your whole year on vacation, you'd become a terrible human being.
Like, no one would like being around you.
You're not producing anything for society.
You know what I'm saying? Like, that would not be good.
But in our mind, we're like, "That would be so great if I could just live on a cruise ship."
Like, go watch the movie WALL-E.
That's what happens when you live on a cruise ship your entire life, right?
Like, they even take the time in the cartoon to like, shrink down, like, do the X-ray.
They don't even have bones. They're gelatinous masses. I'm lazy boys.
You know what I'm saying? Like, they actually take the time.
They really drive the point home, you know?
Someone had to animate that, like the little bones. You know, okay.
But that's what happens to us, right? Happiness and pleasure in this life is seductive in that way.
And so the potential loss of these things can intimidate us into going along with things that we know are not good.
But if we place our hope in Christ alone, okay? It's not Christ and this.
We're not subscribing to Jesus plus, right?
Place my hope in Christ and what? And nothing.
Place my hope in Christ alone. This is the only safeguard. You go, Sam, Babylon sounds terrible and wily.
Yeah, it is. I use the word wily like we're in Looney Tunes right now, right? But it is, it's wily, right?
Man, Sam, Babylon's so wily. It is very wily. How do you avoid it?
Well, actually, it's not very complicated. I've said before, I think I said this last time I preached here. The devil makes everything
complicated, and God makes everything simple, and then we get mad because we feel like God's
oversimplifying it, but we're wrong because we just don't know anything, right? Okay, like that. Yeah.
All right. It's very simple. How do you safeguard yourself? You place your hope in Christ alone.
Philippians chapter 3, verse 7 through 8. Paul used to have things in his life that he valued very greatly.
Things that really mattered a lot, guys. Family, heritage, culture, achievement, academics, education.
Aren't all those good words? It wasn't like he was like, "I used to live a life where I enjoy being, you know, a male prostitute."
No, it's like all good things. Heritage, culture, people, academics, achievement.
That's what Paul says about it in verse 7, Philippians 3. He says, "I once thought these things were valuable."
I used to be seduced by Babylon. That's what he's saying.
But now I consider them worthless because of what Christ has done.
Yes, everything else is worthless when compared with the infinite value of knowing Christ Jesus, my Lord.
For his sake, I have discarded everything else, counting it all as garbage so that I could gain Christ.
And we also have to consider, I said we have to consider we're replacing our hope.
We also have to consider we're replacing our love, right?
Are we placing our love on, like, am I placing my love on me? Right?
Am I placing my love on me? Or am I placing my love on Christ and on others?
See, if the person I'm most in love with is me, I can rationalize doing a lot of terrible things to you.
And especially I can rationalize doing a lot of terrible things to people that I don't even have to look at or see.
You know? Where all these things come from? Oh, they were made by people in this country that you've never seen and you never know their faces.
Okay, that sounds bad, but all right, let's go get some ice cream. Right?
If I mostly care about me, I can justify a lot of treatment towards you.
But if I love Christ first, and then you second, and then me after that, that's my safeguard from being tempted by Babylon.
Because Babylon's going to come and go, "Look what I have." And you're like, "That's not really that appealing to me anymore."
All those things only benefit me. And actually, in the short term, because I'm about to be destroyed with you if I go along, right?
James 1:27, he says, "Pure and genuine religion." That's devotion to Christ, right?
Pure and genuine religion in the sight of God, the Father, means caring for orphans and widows in their distress, and refusing to let the world corrupt you.
Again, in Philippians 3:18, Paul wrote, "For I have told you often before, and I say it again with tears in my eyes,
that there are many whose conduct shows they are really enemies of the cross of Christ."
Guys, he's talking about people who are basically in church, right?
You wouldn't need the phrase, "Their conduct shows they're really enemies of the cross of Christ,"
if you're already talking about unbelievers, right? So he's saying, "There are people amongst us.
There are people in the church, people who believe and call themselves Christian, but their behavior shows that they are
actually the enemies of Jesus, and here's how." They're headed for destruction. Their God is their appetite.
They brag about shameful things, and they think only about this life here on earth.
If I'm primarily thinking about my life right now, and the bills I have right now, and the five kids you're paying for right now,
and, you know, my own comfort right now, again, the avenues for temptation in my life become very well paved, right?
So we have to think about where we're placing our hope and where we're placing our love.
In what ways are you compromised or entangled with Babylon in your life today?
That's what I want us to think about as we wrap up here and move towards the end, right?
This is something each one of us has to do. I couldn't walk around the room, right?
By the way, guys, I am trying myself to get disentangled with Babylon. So, like, I got a lot of work, right?
This is on you, okay? But each one of us have to consider that question.
In what ways am I compromised with Babylon? Am I entangled with Babylon in my life today?
Are you living as a consumer and pursuing pleasure?
Like, is your main perspective on life what you can get out of it?
You know? Church is a great example.
I'm going to this church because I love their worship. Are you kidding me?
Like, guys, that's super normal.
You're participating in an entire Christian family because you're entertained by their musical capability?
Well, when you put it like that, yeah, that's not good, right?
In what ways are we living as consumers and pursuing pleasure?
In what ways are we desiring, again, cultural acceptance and relevance?
In what ways are we idolizing political power?
Questions to think about.
In what ways are we placing trust in the acquisition of wealth and assets?
If I just get this, if I just get this, I will be secure and I will not have to worry.
And then, you know, it's just like the parable of Jesus, and God comes and goes, "You're dying tonight."
And what are you going to do with all that?
Are you finding your identity and achievement and status?
These are all things for us to think about.
These are the trappings of Babylon that compete with allegiance and reliance on God.
You must decide to come out, to come out, to disentangle.
I really want to stick on that word because it's an entanglement, guys.
Anyone ever, like, tried to get, like, a vine out of, like, a chain link fence?
Anyone ever does that yard work? Isn't that fun? No.
30 seconds into getting a vine out of a chain link fence, I rethink every decision I've ever made in my life that has brought me to that point in time.
Like, how did I get here?
Well, it started 10 years ago when I decided to live in this country.
Like, you know what I'm saying? Like, disentangling is a process.
So we're going to have to give it some thought.
You have to decide to come out and disentangle from these things.
For each of us, it will look a little different depending on where we are compromised, okay?
This isn't a command to leave America and be a hermit, right?
Like, again, like, it wasn't just like, "Leave the Roman Empire. Go live in the wilderness."
Some people did that, but that wasn't the command, right?
This is about nonconformity.
You can even go back to the way that, like, Jeremiah would write to the exiles when they were literally living in the city of Babylon.
And he's like, "While you are in Babylon, live like this so that you are different from Babylon while you live in Babylon," right?
So that is not God saying, "You need to go, like, be a hermit in the woods and, like, you know, go buy a private island somewhere and stick up like a Christian commune."
Sounds kind of awesome, actually, but that's not what God is telling us to do, right?
It's about nonconformity.
1 Peter 2:11 says, "Dear friends, I warn you," look at his language, "as temporary residents and foreigners," right?
The idea is that you're living in a land you don't truly belong because you belong to the kingdom of God, right?
He goes, "I warn you, as people who are, like, temporary residents and foreigners, to keep away from worldly desires that wage war against your very souls,
be careful to live properly among your unbelieving neighbors, then even if they accuse you of doing wrong,
they will see your honorable behavior and they will give honor to God when He judges the world."
So again, consider the question, what would it look like maybe for you to live differently from Babylon?
If Babylon is greed, exploitation, self-idolizing pride, and indulgence, the alternative looks more like generosity, justice, charity, humility,
and here's one of the most important things to stand against the prostitute of Babylon: self-control.
It's a fruit of the Spirit, right? With the Lord, I actually have an imbued capacity from God Himself to begin to exercise control over me, right?
And this is what the people who are having their fun with Babylon don't have. That's why they're so easily pulled in and duped.
All right, so we live in this world as a blessing in this world. We're able to live in this world as a blessing in this world while not conforming to this world because this is actually what Jesus pioneered for us, and this is how I want us to close today.
What I'm describing is hard, and it's a process, and it requires a lot of prayer and discernment, and it's going to require no small amount of fortitude, okay?
And you might be listening going, "Sam, I hear you. I agree with you. I don't know if I can do this."
You can. I mean, you can't, but like, Jesus pioneered the way for you, demonstrated how to do it, and is now working in you through His Spirit to actually empower you to do it.
So yes, correct. On your own, you are, yeah, you're not going to make it.
Through Christ, through devotion to Him, He will actually enable and empower this for you, and He has demonstrated what it looks like. Think of it. He lived, Jesus lived in the Roman Empire, guys.
He lived in the Roman Empire while remaining completely disentangled from it.
So He already did it, and you can show us how to do it, and you can enable us to do it.
I'm going to read this last verse, and then we're going to close with a song here.
Therefore, this is Hebrews 12, since we are surrounded by such a huge crowd of witnesses to the life of faith, let us strip off every weight that slows us down,
and especially the sin that so easily trips us up, and let us run with endurance the race God has set before us.
We do this by keeping our eyes on Jesus, the champion who initiates and perfects our faith.
Because of the joy awaiting him, he endured the cross, disregarding its shame, and now he is seated in the place of honor beside God's throne.
Think of all the hostility he endured from sinful people. Then you won't become weary and give up.
So, Jesus is the one who inspires us. He's the one who enables us to do these things, okay?
There is an old song. Okay, I say old, and then some of you are older than me, and you can be like, "Sam, that's not old. You're just young."
I think it's old because it's like 90s, okay? All right? We just judge the room. Some people go, "Oh, yeah," and some people are like, "Haha, youngin." Okay?
It might be older than 90s. I know it from the 90s. I used to sing it with a youth group all the time.
And I thought today, let's end by singing a simple and pure devotion to God, asking Him, as we're hearing this,
as we're wrestling through, how do I even start to do this in my life? Again,
God makes things simple. So this is a simple song. Some of the older songs, by the way,
are so much better because they're so simple. There's like not even like three verses, by the way.
Okay. That's worship team stuff, but they're so simple. All right. So if you know the song, sing with me right away.
If you don't, you will know it very quickly because it's not complicated.
Okay, thanks.
So we're going to close. I'm just going to invite you guys to sing the song with me, right?
There's all different kinds of ways we can engage our spirit and our mind with the Lord.
And one of those is through song, right? So we're going to go ahead. We're going to sing this. And as we sing it,
I just really invite you to let your mind and your heart and your soul really soak on the words,
really think about what we're singing, and just say today, God, like, I don't know how I'm going to do all this,
but I'm devoting myself to you, and I'm asking you to lead me. It's a step-by-step process, okay?
Oh God, you are my God, and I will ever praise you. Oh God, you are my God, and I will ever praise you. I will seek you
in the morning, and I will learn to walk in your ways, and step by step you lead me, and I will follow you all of my days. Oh God, you are
my God, and I will ever praise you. Oh God, you are my God, and I will ever praise you. And I will seek you in the morning.
And I will learn to walk in your ways. And step by step, you lead me. And I will follow you all of my days. And I will follow you all of my days.
Oh, I will follow you all of my days. And step by step, you lead me. And I will follow you all of my days. And I will seek you in the morning.
And I will learn to walk in your ways. And step by step, you lead me. And I will follow you all of my days.
Lord, I pray that you would receive the song, Lord, that you would receive our hearts devoted to you. Lord, I pray that in your mercy, Lord God, your mercy for our weakness, your mercy for our foolishness, Lord, that you would instruct us and teach us the way to go, God.
Lord, even now we're conscious of just how easily we're tricked, how easily we're made to be complicit in things that are not from you, things that you have to destroy, God.
So as you tell us to come out from these things, Lord, would you show each of us what are those things that we have to come out from in our lives?
In your mercy, God, show us this at an achievable rate for us. As you lead us, and as you know each one of our situations, God, just give us the wisdom.
And I also pray that you would give us the courage to move in the direction where you point us, God.
So thank you for these things. I pray for your blessing in each of us today as we go, Lord God, every house and home that is represented here.
We thank you for these things, Lord, in your name. Amen.